A Guide to the Cardwell Machine Company (Richmond, Va.) Records, 1853-1993
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Cardwell Machine Company (Richmond, Va.) Records, 1853-1993
The Library of Virginia
37136
5.125 cubic feet (12 boxes) and 121 volumes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Carwell Machine Company, Richmond.
Historical Information
The Cardwell Machine Company in Richmond, Virginia was formed in 1891 with the merger of H. W. Smith & Co. and John W. Cardwell & Co. Both firms manufactured farm implements. Following the merger, Cardwell Machine Company steadily increased its concentration on the tobacco processing and handling field, and became leaders in the manufacture of machinery for the separating, threshing, classifying, and screening of tobacco. The company also produced feed regulators, ordering and conditioning cylinders, sand reels, blenders, tie leaf cutters, tipping machines, belt conveyors, and quality control equipment. In 1963, the company moved to South Richmond. Cardwell was acquired by Arenco of Stockholm, Sweden in 1974, and became part of the Arenco Tobacco Machinery Group, and continued to design, fabricate, and ship their machinery to customers in North and South America and the Far East.
Scope and Content
Records, 1853-1993, of the Cardwell Machine Company in Richmond, Virginia, including advertising materials, appraisals and inventories, cashbooks, catalogs and price lists, contract books, correspondence, daybooks, drawings, ephemera, ledgers, order books, patent records, payroll and time records, photographs, and sales books and literature.
Artifacts, including a wooden cutting machine and a patent model for a barrel press, are housed in Special Collections.
Contents List
- Account Book, 1893-1894. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- W.A. Adams Company, 1914-1948. (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
- Advertising. (Box 9)
- Advertising Scrapbook. (Box 9)
- Appraisal of the Cardwell Machine Company, 31 August 1919. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Appraisal Summaries of the Cardwell Machine Company, 31 August 1919. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Appraisal Summaries of Equipment of the Virginia Forging & Manufacturing Company, 15 September 1920. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Arenco. (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
- Arenco. (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Bank Protests, 1907-1908. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Bills Receivable, 1877-1889. (Volume 1)
- Bills Receivable, 1890-1917. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Blotters. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Bond Coupons. (Box 2, Folder 7-11)
- British American Tobacco Company, 1938. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Brown and Williamson Tobacco Corporation, 1938. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Capital Stock Tax, 1918. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Cardwell Family Tree. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Cashbook No. 1, 1877-1893. (Volume 2)
- Cashbook (Factory No. 2), 1892-1893. (Volume 3)
- Cashbook, 1897-1900. (Volume 4)
- Cashbook, 1916-1922. (Volume 5)
- Cashbook B (J.W. Cardwell and Company), 1875-1881. (Volume 6)
- Cashbook C (J.W. Cardwell and Company), 1882-1887. (Volume 7)
- Cashbook A, 1890-1893. (Volume 8)
- Cashbook B, 1894-1897. (Volume 9)
- Cashbook C, 1898-1901. (Volume 10)
- Cashbook D, 1902-1905. (Volume 11)
- Cashbook E, 1905-1908. (Volume 12)
- Cashbook F, 1908-1911. (Volume 13)
- Cashbook G, 1911-1914. (Volume 14)
- Cashbook H, 1914-1916. (Volume 15)
- Cashbook I, 1916-1919. (Volume 16)
- Cashbook J, 1919-1921. (Volume 17)
- Cashbook, 1921-1923. (Volume 18)
- Cashbook, 1925-1927. (Volume 19)
- Cashbook, 1927-1929. (Volume 20)
- Cashbook, 1930-1932. (Volume 21)
- Cashbook, 1929-1934. (Volume 22)
- Cashbook, 1934-1937. (Volume 23)
- Cashbook, 1937-1939. (Volume 24)
- Cashbook, 1939-1941. (Volume 25)
- Cashbook, 1941-1945. (Volume 26)
- Cashbook, 1948-1957. (Volume 27)
- Catalogue of Farm Machinery and Agricultural Implements - H.M. Smith & Co., 1884. (Box 3)
- Catalogues and Price Lists. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Check Register, 22001-23000, 1 May 1925 - 10 July 1926. (Volume 28)
- Check Register, 23001-24000, 15 July 1926 - 10 August 1927. (Volume 29)
- Check Register, 25001-26000 15 July 1929 - 11 October 1930. (Volume 30)
- Clipping re: Industrial Archaeology, 1967. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Contract, 1927. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Contract Book 2, A3400-A5599, 4 October 1924 - 30 July 1925. (Volume 31)
- Contract Book 3, A5600-A7499, 30 July 1925 - 2 April 1926. (Volume 32)
- Contract Book 4, A7500-A9299, 2 April 1926 - 30 October 1926. (Volume 33)
- Contract Book 5, A9542-B563, 1 December 1926 - 13 June 1927. (Volume 34)
- Contract Book 6, B876-B2650, 27 July 1927 - 29 March 1928. (Volume 35)
- Contract Book 7, B2651-B4200, 29 March 1928 - 30 October 1928. (Volume 36)
- Contract Book 8, B4201-B5599, 30 October 1928 - 19 June 1929. (Volume 37)
- Contract Book 9, B5600-B7000, 20 June 1929 - 5 February 1930. (Volume 38)
- Contract Book 10, B7001-B8625, 6 February 1930 - 12 December 1930. (Volume 39)
- Contract Book 11, B8626-C160, 12 December 1930 - 4 April 1932. (Volume 40)
- Contract Book 12, C161-C1700, 4 April 1932 - 3 October 1933. (Volume 41)
- Contract Book 13, C1701-C3150, 3 October 1933 - 30 March 1935. (Volume 42)
- Contract Book 14, C3151-C4599, 1 April 1935 - 13 August 1936. (Volume 43)
- Contract Book 15, C4600-C6000, 13 August 1936 - 6 October 1937. (Volume 44)
- Contract Book 16, C6001-C7500, 8 October 1937 - 6 April 1939. (Volume 45)
- Contract Book 17, C7501-C9000, 7 April 1939 - 28 August 1940. (Volume 46)
- Contract Book 18, C9001-D499, 29 August 1940 - 21 April 1942. (Volume 47)
- Contract Book 19, D500-D1899, 21 April 1942 - 24 February 1944. (Volume 48)
- Contract Book 20, D1900-D3199, 24 February 1944 - 31 August 1945. (Volume 49)
- Contract Book 21, D3200-D4399, 31 August 1945 -10 January 1947. (Volume 50)
- Contract Book 22, D4400-D5599, 10 January 1947 - 26 May 1948. (Volume 51)
- Contract Book 23, D5600-D6800, 26 May 1948 - 26 October 1949. (Volume 52)
- Contract List, B8273-D1774, 1 October 1930 - 31 December 1943. (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
- Contract List, B8273-D1774, 1 October 1930 - 31 December 1943. (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
- Control Forms for Price List Sheets, 1959-1973. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Cost Record and Selling Price, 1902-1955. (Volume 53)
- Cost Record and Selling Price, 1920-1937. (Volume 54)
- Davenport Manufacturing Company. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Daybook, 1 February 1890 - July 1891. (Volume 55)
- Daybook (Factory No. 2), 1 January 1892 - 30 June 1894. (Volume 56)
- Daybook, 3 July - 28 December 1894. (Volume 57)
- Directory of Oil Mills, Companies, and Executives, 1906-1925. (Volume 58)
- Directory of Tobacco Companies and Executives, 1906-1925. (Volume 59)
- Drawings/Illustrations. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Drawings/Illustrations. (Box 10-11)
- Ephemera. (Box 12)
- John J. Greer & Co., 1940-1943. (Box 4, Folder 7-13)
- John J. Greer & Co., 1944-1949. (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
- History. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Hydraulic Control Panels. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Hydraulic Power Units. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Hydraulic Test Panels. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Incorporation Act (Amendment and Revision), 1892. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Index of Half Tone Cuts. (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Installation. (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Inventories (Union Manufacturing Company) and Order Book (J.W. Cardwell & Co.), 1861-1868, 1881-1892. (Volume 60)
- Inventories, 1894-1896. (Volume 61)
- Irvine Box Shook Machine. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Journal A (Daybook), 1 January 1890- 30 September 1892. (Volume 62)
- Journal B (Daybook), 1 October 1892 - 30 April 1894. (Volume 63)
- Journal C (Daybook), 1 May 1894 - 24 July 1895. (Volume 64)
- Journal D (Daybook), 24 July 1895 - 31 December 1896. (Volume 65)
- Journal E (Daybook), 2 January 1897 - 31 May 1898. (Volume 66)
- Journal F (Daybook), 1 June 1898 - 30 August 1899. (Volume 67)
- Journal G (Daybook), 1 September 1899 - 31 December 1900. (Volume 68)
- Journal H (Daybook), 1 January - 31 December 1901. (Volume 69)
- Journal (Daybook), 1 March 1921 - 31 March 1925. (Volume 70)
- Journal (Daybook), 31 March 1925 - 13 February 1929. (Volume 71)
- Journal (Daybook), March 1929 - November 1937. (Volume 72)
- Journal No. 1 (Daybook), 1 February 1887 - 7 April 1891. (Volume 73)
- W.B. Lea Tobacco Company, 1931-1948. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Ledger, 1870-1875. (Volume 74)
- Ledger D (J. W. Cardwell and Company), 1881-1891. (Volume 75)
- Ledger A (Factory No. 2), 1892-1893. (Volume 76)
- Ledger B, 1893-1895. (Volume 77)
- Index to Ledger B, 1893-1895. (Volume 78)
- Ledger C, 1895-1899. (Volume 79)
- Index to Ledger C, 1895-1899. (Volume 80)
- Ledger D, 1899-1902. (Volume 81)
- Index to Ledger D, 1899-1902. (Volume 82)
- Ledger No. 1, 1887-1892. (Volume 83)
- Ledger A, 1890-1892. (Volume 84)
- City Ledger, 1903-1913. (Volume 85)
- City Ledger, 1903-1915. (Volume 86)
- City Ledger, 1907-1928. (Volume 87)
- Ledger, 1903-1936. (Volume 88)
- Ledger, 1916-1920. (Volume 89)
- Ledger, 1924-1928. (Volume 90)
- Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company, 1939-1949. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Literature Control Numbers. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Literature - Filter Division. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Literature - Hydraulics. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Literature - Tobacco. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Literature - Woodworking. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Machine List. (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
- Machinery Instructions/Directions. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Material for Board Room Mural. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous. (Box 6, Folder 10)
- News Releases. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Open House, 17 June 1964. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Order Book (Original Charges), 2 January - 30 December 1892. (Volume 91)
- Order Book No. 1 (Original Charges), 2 January - 27 December 1893. (Volume 92)
- Order Book No. 1 (Original Charges), 2 January - 29 June 1894. (Volume 93)
- Order Book, 2 January 1895 - 1 May 1896. (Volume 94)
- Order Book, 1 February 1896 - 5 February 1897. (Volume 95)
- Order Book, 1 July 1903 - 21 November 1904. (Volume 96)
- Order Book, 21 December 1928 - 15 April 1943. (Volume 97)
- Patents. (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Pay Roll, 20 June 1912 - 14 January 1920. (Volume 98)
- Pay Roll, 28 January 1920 - 18 May 1927. (Volume 99)
- Peanut Machinery - Correspondence, Literature, etc., 1931-1933. (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Permit to Encroach, 1952. (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Photo Album, 1974-1990. (Box 6, Folder 16-18)
- Photographs. (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
- Photographs. (Box 11)
- Photographs - Cyanotype. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Presses. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Production Estimates. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Classifier and Tangential Parts, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Hassock Stands, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Hogshead Machines and Parts, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Industrial Equipment - Not Pumps, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Installation Work, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Machine Shop Work, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Miscellaneous Parts, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Movable Presses, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Ordering Drums, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Peanut Machinery, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Power Units (Industrial), 1954. (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Power Units (Tobacco Industry), 1954. (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Press and Pump Parts, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Service Work (Other Than Tobacco Industry), 1954. (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Shop Maintenance, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Production Order Cost Recap - Tobacco Presses, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Promissory Notes, 1909, 1911. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Purchase Journal, 1931-1932. (Volume 100)
- Receipt Book (William H. Beare/Samuel Freedley & Co./William Fraser & Co.), 1853-1869. (Volume 101)
- Sales Book C (Daybook), 2 October 1876 - 21 June 1879. (Volume 102)
- Sales and Journal D (Daybook), 23 June 1879 - 30 June 1882. (Volume 103)
- Sales and Journal E (Daybook), 1 July 1882 - 31 January 1887. (Volume 104)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1902 - 31 December 1905. (Volume 105)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1906 - 31 December 1908. (Volume 106)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1909 - 8 December 1911. (Volume 107)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1912 - 10 December 1914. (Volume 108)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1915 - 31 December 1918. (Volume 109)
- Sales Book, 2 January 1919 - 27 March 1920. (Volume 110)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1924 - 31 December 1925. (Volume 111)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1926 - 31 December 1927. (Volume 112)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1928 - 31 December 1929. (Volume 113)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1930 - 31 December 1932. (Volume 114)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1933 - 31 December 1935. (Volume 115)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1936 - 31 December 1939. (Volume 116)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1940 - 31 December 1943. (Volume 117)
- Sales Book, 1 January 1944 - 31 December 1947. (Volume 118)
- Sales Literature. (Box 8, Folder 2)
- W.O. Smith & Co., 1940-1943. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Speech to VACARPS by Charles A. Hotchkiss, 21 March 1984. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Stationary. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- "The Third World Comes Home," Richmond Times - Dispatch, 24 November 1985. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Time Book. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Time Book, 29 July 1919 - 31 July 1920. (Volume 119)
- Time Book, 2 August 1920 - 11 November 1924. (Volume 120)
- Tobacco (Weekly Trade Review), 1928, 1950. (Box 9)
- Tobacco Machinery - Correspondence, 1931-1941. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Tobacco Merchants Association - President's Address, 1920. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Trial Balances. (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
- Trial Balances. (Box 9)
- Trial Balances. (Volume 121)
- Valentine Museum. (Box 8, Folder 12)